Hi again,
let's explore some of the common tools for
effectively communicating with your
project team and stakeholders.
In this video, we'll focus on messaging,
virtual meetings and
work management and collaboration tools.
Let's start with messaging and email.
Email is standard for
business communications, so
it's important to streamline
the number of emails that you send out.
At Google, I get tons of emails a day.
It's a lot of work to figure out which
ones I need to read immediately,
which ones can wait and
which ones require a reply right away.
It's important that you understand how
to use email in a professional context.
A quick internet search will provide
you with lots of tips and examples.
Here's some of my key tips for you to
keep in mind, carefully select who you're
sending an email to, and most importantly,
be conscious of why you're sending it.
Make sure the subject field clearly
states what the email is about.
If it's urgent or requires a response,
add that to the subject and
the first line of the email.
Keep your messages as short as
possible and stay on topic.
If there's a lot of information to share,
consider placing the information
into a digital document you can link or
attach to the email.
Then summarize what you
want readers to focus on.
If there's a specific action you need
from the recipient, state it clearly so
that they understand what's
expected of them and when.
Your language choices matter, so
avoid slang, acronyms, and shortcuts for
words that might be more appropriate for
texts.
And one more thing,
write in an appropriate tone for
the person receiving the email.
It's generally best practice to be
friendly, motivating, clear, and specific.
As I mentioned earlier, most people,
especially other managers, directors and
executive get lots of emails.
With that in mind,
you may want to consider instant messaging
tools like Google Meet or Slack.
This can be an alternative to email
when you just have a quick question, or
update or as a way to alert someone
to please check their inbox.
Instant messaging helps
reduce back and forth emails or
phone calls that can quickly clear up
miscommunications or let you know if and
when you should take
an issue to a meeting.
Be mindful of when you decide
to use instant messaging.
This kind of quick communication could
lead to distraction and informality.
It can easily become an outlet to
share non work related information or
information that sensitive or
confidential.
It can also be difficult
to track instant messages.
Later on, if you need to reference
information that you chatted about,
you might not be able to easily
find it with instant messaging.
It's a good idea to ask people's
preferences on how they like to be
communicated with.
Even if instant messaging is faster
the person might prefer to use email.
With experience, you'll be able
to determine the most effective
ways to communicate with your team.
Next up, we'll discuss some tools for
remote meetings.
Virtual meeting tools like Google Meet and
Zoom are great for
communicating, especially as
remote work becomes more standard.
Better yet, each of these tools are easy
to access and easy to learn how to use.
Well run online meetings can be
extremely effective, they allow you and
your team to interact in real-time.
Which can help boost morale and
create a sense of team when it's not
possible to be together in person.
Virtual meetings can be highly engaging,
as attendees can access and
share files during the meeting.
And then there are work management and
collaboration tools like Google Drive,
Asana, and Smartsheet.
These kinds of tools make it easier to
share information among teams, even better
with work management and collaboration
tools information sharing goes both ways.
Team members can easily update
their progress without the need for
extra meetings or phone calls.
These tools can accomplish many different
things like tracking progress on tasks,
deliverables, and milestones.
They can also help you to manage a budget,
build helpful charts and diagrams,
manage contracts and licenses and
keep stakeholders informed.
Work management and collaboration tools
allow you to focus your communications
within the context of specific tasks,
project details and timeline.
Rather than writing an email and linking
to the relevant information when you're
working and communicating in a tool,
the information is already there in one
place for easy reference and
decision making.
Another great aspect of these kinds
of tools is that the work gets done
in real time.
These tools allow remote
teams to collaborate and
communicate as though they're physically
working in the same office together.
Encouraging your teams to check in and
update their progress regularly helps to
maintain the real-time feel of
interacting with coworkers.
There are many different types
of work management software
that automatically make project
planning and tracking a lot easier.
And they are much more efficient
than manual project tracking.
A quick word of caution before
we move on the use, access or
sharing of confidential or
need to know information externally,
including financial and business data,
user data and information about our
products and services is likely prohibited
unless you're given explicit permission.
When using shared work management tools,
just be mindful of who wants and
needs access
versus who doesn't need access, to do your
part in keeping important data safe.
There are so many different ways
to share information to your team,
whether if through meetings, emails, instant
messages, spreadsheets, and trackers.
By becoming familiar with some of
the more common communication tools,
you can choose the right one for
your project needs.
Now you've learned a bit more about
the importance of team communication and
some tools that effectively communicate
and foster collaboration within your team.
In the next video,
we'll learn how to organize and
facilitate team meetings
to ensure project success.
I'll meet you there.